Previously on Gotham:
- Alfred. The manor.
- It's my fault.
Mr. Cobblepot.
Guns!
This never would have happened
if you stayed with me.
You're having a baby with Barbara.
- Don't think I'm fit to be a mother?
- What do you think?
You live in Gotham.
I believe the time has come
for a change of scenery.
You found a way out of Gotham?
It's a submarine.
Reunification with the mainland
hangs on by a thread.
Toxic chemicals rain down on to the city
and the government cuts us adrift
for good.
Gotham's golden rule, no heroes.
No heroes.
Watch out for him.
He thinks he's a white knight.
He's a loose cannon.
You two here
to pick up your grandchildren?
Come on, Babs.
You got the only full bar in Gotham.
And if you, two dinosaurs,
wanna keep coming here,
you better up your intel.
We got a lead
on some black market heating oil.
One drink, to share.
Then you go wheeze to death
somewhere else.
Would you look at that?
Dix, look at you,
up and walking around,
you old son of a gun.
I've been looking for you two for a while.
You found us.
You two ever think about the past?
What we did?
- What are you talking about, Dix?
- About her.
About what we did to the girl.
Who is that?
It is like the living death in here.
Enough of this.
Hey, Gramps.
Can you please repeat your story
for Mr. Wayne, Madame?
We live in the shelter on West End.
There are so many of us crammed in there.
So much uncertainty. Fear.
And with the river poisoned,
it should have been awful,
but people came together, made it a home.
- What happened?
- A couple of weeks ago,
we heard rumours about something
underneath the building.
Where it connects to the sewer.
Then people started going missing.
Hank, my husband...
wanted to look for them.
Said we were a family.
So the two of you went searching for them.
It was so dark.
I didn't see what attacked us.
I hit my head and when I woke up,
Hank was gone.
Please, Mr. Wayne.
We have a daughter.
We'll do everything we can.
Should we tell Gordon?
Why, he's stretched thin as it is.
Alfred, we don't know who or what
is down there.
We know there's a man down there
in danger,
and we know this lady sent for us.
So go on, then,
what do you think we should do?
Let's go find him.
Under normal circumstances,
I wouldn't have called you
for a couple of stiffs.
What do you normally do
when a couple of your patrons
- get stabbed?
- Bury the bodies.
Find out who did it
and then bury those bodies.
See, that's not something
you should be telling a cop.
We're living in a different world, Harvey.
- So why did you call us?
- Take a look.
- Boggs and Lewis.
- You know them?
They were cops.
They were gone before you joined.
- What happened?
- They came around.
Peddling third-rate intel.
It was closing time, so I let them in
and then some other fossil knifed them.
- You saw him?
- Yeah, he must have snuck in.
Looked like a cop too. These two knew him.
Bartender said
they called him Micks, Hicks.
- Dix?
- Maybe.
No way.
Dix was Harvey's old partner.
Oh, there we go. Case closed.
So you're telling me this guy
rolled in here in a wheelchair,
stabbed these two, and rolled on out?
He wasn't in a wheelchair.
Then it couldn't be Dix.
He's been paralysed for the last 15 years.
Harvey, you're confusing me
with someone who cares.
I called you as a courtesy,
and now I'm wishing I just
dumped these two corpses in an alley.
Do we even know that Dix
is still in Gotham after the bridges blew?
I heard he moved into an apartment
about a year ago.
I meant to check up on him,
but it can't be him.
I hear what you're saying,
but we should still talk to him.
Maybe he knows something.
Fine.
How are you feeling?
I'm fine. Thanks for asking.
Look, I've been giving you space,
but we have to talk
about how this is gonna work.
I'm gonna be a part of this kid's life.
Oh, you seem pretty confident about that.
I am.
Reunification is gonna happen.
You should think about what kind of person
you wanna be when it does.
It's a chance for you to start anew.
I like who I am.
You were due hours ago.
Yes, I was. But I had to get us lunch.
- And I met Dale.
- I see that.
Do you see this?
Our secret plan to get off this island?
Relax. Dale is completely trustworthy.
How do you know we can trust him
if you just met him?
Because he's mute and dumb as a post.
Look, I know you're paranoid
about people watching us...
Someone is watching us!
Why do you think I installed
this alarm system?
And as safe as I feel
with your jingle bell contraption
in place,
I went out and procured us some muscle.
You're welcome.
At least you're doing something.
How's my SS Gertrud coming along?
Our submarine is coming along just fine,
thank you.
I've been working on the sonar,
which turns out as far more complex
than I anticipated.
Well, I am confident
you will figure it out.
Of course I will figure it out.
Because I figure everything out.
The navigation system.
The oxygen exchange.
I will figure everything out
because I'm the only one working!
- This was supposed to be a partnership.
- It is!
I already did my part by stealing
everything valuable in Gotham,
- all of which you get half.
- No!
Your goons stole it.
And then you killed them.
Are you expecting someone?
Who would I be expecting, Oswald?
I told you someone's watching us.
Dale, go do what I pay you for.
Protect us!
Wait.
Penn?
Hello, Mr. Cobblepot.
Are you really...?
- I don't believe it. You're alive.
- Indeed, sir. I am.
But you were shot. I was there.
This whole time I thought you were dead,
but you're alive.
But you're only coming to me now?
I'm so terribly sorry, Mr. Cobblepot.
I wanted to come see you, but...
he wouldn't let me.
He? He who?
Mr. Cobblepot.
This is...
Mr. Scarface.
Wonderful.
Look, I'm sure Dix is in the clear,
but we do have to ask.
That's not it.
It's just that I feel that
I should've been by him before,
I'm all he's got.
Well, look, Guido, right?
Dix!
- What the heck?
- Bullock?
- Is that you?
- Yeah.
- Don't shoot.
- Okay.
Come in.
Is that the way
you always answer the door?
Nowadays you can't be too careful.
Especially someone like me.
A kid comes in,
he'd cut my throat for a cup of soup.
Anyway, I wasn't expecting you.
Figured you forgot about me.
Look, look, when the bridges came down
- and I got busy and...
- Oh, sure, sure. You forgot me.
Everybody forgets.
I didn't forget.
Planning on taking a trip?
Maybe.
I like to keep a bag packed just in case.
Yeah, where were you last night?
Where was I? I was right here.
Anybody else here with you?
Anybody that can back up your story?
You're asking me if I was out there
killing Boggs and Lewis?
Does it look like I was out there
So you heard about that?
I'm gonna tell you something.
If it meant that I can get out
of this son of a gun wheelchair,
I would confess right here and now
to Boggs, to Lewis,
to anybody you want me to confess to.
All right, fine.
But if you were detective,
what would you say if you were us?
We come in here,
you're packing a suitcase.
I would say that I did it, which I didn't,
or I'd be very worried that I'd be next.
What do you mean, "You being next?"
What's your connection to Boggs and Lewis?
Now, come on, what?
Nothing.
I just work with them. That's it.
We... we worked the case together.
- Four of you?
- Yeah.
Dix wasn't my partner then.
I was a rookie cop.
- Wet behind the ears.
- So what was the case?
A woman killed her husband,
as far as I can remember,
it was pretty open and shut.
But at least we can agree
that Dix didn't walk into The Sirens
and stabbed those two guys.
So who did?
Barbara said Boggs and Lewis
recognised the killer.
They called him Dix.
We come in here, he's packing a suitcase,
he shoots at us, this stinks, Harvey.
Hey.
You all right?
What the hell?
These basements run along Gotham sewers.
The river is right next to it.
You mean the river filled
with Jeremiah's toxins?
Who knows what kind of damage
these chemicals could do.
Yeah, you're right.
It's just that you talked to Renee.
Hold on.
Bite marks.
- Animal?
- I say human I've never seen.
Whatever it was...
it dragged him that way.
Seems like human skin.
Here's the file you asked for,
Victoria Cartwright.
How did you...
I had Harper run every case
the four of you worked,
cross-referenced with any woman
that killed her husband.
Do I need to read it?
You're gonna tell me what's in it.
Victoria Cartwright was a banker.
She led a very boring life.
Until she snapped
and put two .38 calibre slugs
into her husband. End of story.
You guys rehearsed that?
It says there was no physical evidence.
She was convicted on the statement
of her 7-year-old daughter, Jane.
This was 20 years ago. Where's Jane now?
What's the point? The killer was a man,
a man that can imitate frigging faces.
What was the name of the guy that Strange
got to imitate you?
A Basil something.
That's who we should be looking for.
That was different and you know it.
Do you have an address for this Jane?
No. But the family's old home
is in the Green Zone.
- Just east of the clinic.
- Jim, it's a dead end.
Is there anything else you wanna tell me?
You know what, why don't you hang back?
Whoa, whoa, wait. Are you benching me?
Killer's still out there.
Keep an eye on your partner.
Penn, Arnold.
It's Arthur.
- You're holding a doll.
- It's not a doll.
It's a dummy.
Oh, this is great. I'm going back to work.
Excuse me.
You're saying he made you come here?
Mr. Scarface is very persuasive.
Persuasive?
He made me tell him about your...
treasure.
Penn...
I think you need a rest.
And perhaps a psychiatrist.
Then we can discuss you
resuming your former duties.
Obviously, I won't pay you
for the time you were gone--
Shut your pie-hole!
This the one you were telling me about?
- Punk who thinks he's in charge?
- Yes, sir.
That's Mr. Cobblepot.
Oswald, if you won't make him leave,
I will.
- Yeah.
- No one's going anywheres.
Penn, show these dewdroppers
we're serious.
Forgive me.
Now, let's talk turkey, turkeys.
- What a mess, huh?
- Yeah.
Boggs and Lewis were idiots.
Complete idiots.
They should have known when they see
a guy walking, then it ain't me.
You think the Cartwright girl
said something?
How would I know?
So how've you been
since the bridges came down?
You getting enough food? Medicine?
What if I said no?
I'd feel like crap.
Then no.
The Cartwright girl is dead.
A buddy of mine who was a screw-over
at Arkham.
He said she was an inmate there
and she died a couple of years ago, so...
this has nothing to do with her.
GCPD. We're coming in.
Check upstairs.
Looks like this place has been abandoned
since before the bridges came down.
Yeah.
What the hell?
What the hell was that?
Someone's been living here.
What's that smell?
Everything all right?
All good. No one's here.
Hey.
Don't look at me. Don't look at me!
We found your handiwork.
Nothing to say?
You're gonna have to take that mask off.
The only way you're gonna keep
that mask on is if you talk.
Otherwise, I'm gonna reach out
at this table
and I'm gonna rip it off your face.
- Who are you?
- Nobody.
You're not Jane Cartwright?
Because you were in her childhood home.
You're about the right age.
Talk to me, Jane.
I know after your mother was convicted,
you ended up a ward of the state.
In and out of institutions
until you ended up at Arkham.
Then you vanished.
Some say died.
- What happened to you?
- Me?
Nothing happened to me.
Okay.
What happened to Jane?
Well...
Lots happened to Jane.
She was taken from Arkham.
Down, down, down.
The doctor did things to her.
Experiments on her and others.
Are you talking about Hugo Strange?
You were taken to Indian Hill?
The professor was obsessed
with the power to change.
The way a chameleon would change its skin.
He wanted humans to have that power.
He made it so Jane could change her skin,
her bones, her hair,
the colour of her eyes.
All it takes is a single touch
and her body becomes a mirror.
And when it's done,
she sheds her skin and starts anew.
It remembers everyone it touched.
It's touched you, Detective.
We can help you, Miss Cartwright.
Jane Cartwright is dead.
She died in Arkham.
That's when Jane Doe was born.
So why kill all these cops?
You wanna know why they died?
Ask your friend.
What is that?
Heck.
We should head out.
My battery is dying...
Please. He's coming. He's coming.
Who's coming? What happened?
He's going to kill me. I barely got away.
- Are you Hank?
- Yes.
Your wife sent us.
Is there anyone else left below down here?
They're all dead.
Oh, God. Oh, God. Oh, God.
Hank! Hank! Hold on, Hank!
Hand over the heaters.
If you don't mind.
Mr. Penn, can't we just talk this through?
Get back!
I'm so sorry.
At least tell me what happened
after Haven.
Help me to understand this.
Go on.
Sing your song.
After I was shot...
I woke up in the GCPD morgue.
I was alone. I...
I patched my wounds
as best I could and crawled out.
I hid in a store.
An abandoned magic shop.
That's where Mr. Scarface found me.
And he told me all about you.
How you used him.
Chewed him up and spat him out!
Treated him like a palooka!
- That's a lie!
- Oh, please, Oswald.
It's what you do.
Arnold...
Arthur, what do you want?
I don't want anything.
But Mr. Scarface, well...
He wants your treasure.
And to be boss.
Really? The dummy wants
to be the boss of Gotham?
Bingo!
Now give me the key to your treasure room.
Why would I do that?
You're obviously gonna kill me anyway.
What am I doing?
- I'm talking to a doll!
- Dummy.
- Seriously?
- You know what, Oswald?
Honestly, you deserve this.
- Nobody asked you.
- You are opportunistic!
Your loyalty is shaky at best!
And you will hurt anyone,
anyone to get what you want.
I hardly think you're one to throw stones.
Listen, Penn...
Eyes down here, pal.
Sorry. Mr. Scarface,
I got a question for you.
Shoot.
After you get your...
tiny wooden hands on that treasure,
what are you gonna do?
Where are you gonna go?
People are gonna come after you
eventually.
Then I'll...
I'll take them all on!
Yeah. Show them who's boss.
You wouldn't have to do that
if you could get off this island now,
would you?
What are you doing?
Shut it! Let the smart one talk.
How do you feel about submarines?
What are we doing here?
I just wanted to take us someplace quiet
where we could talk.
- You did a bad thing.
- Oh, come on. Not that again.
We put a killer in jail, all right?
What do you keep moping about?
She was guilty.
She got what she deserved. Drop it.
Did you get what you deserved?
What?
You made that girl into a murderer.
Oh, come on.
You, your friends...
- the kid.
- Come on, you...
I'm gonna make sure
you never do that again.
Harper, where is Dix?
I saw Bullock take him in the back.
Barbara, what are you doing here?
Seems my bartender overheard
the killer say something
before he ice picked Harvey's pals.
I thought I be a good citizen.
Okay.
"The kid's guilty too."
The kid.
Listen, what you said before
about me being a known criminal,
I was on some list your army buddy had.
When the government rolls in,
am I gonna be arrested?
Honestly, I don't know.
But that would work out for you, right?
I go to jail, you get the baby.
I don't want that.
Is that a promise?
I go straight, I'm clear?
Stay right here.
Hey, Harvey. Where did you take Dix?
I didn't take Dix anywhere.
Oh, God.
She got into your locker,
must have taken your clothes.
We have to lockdown the GCPD.
Hey, Harvey...
We'll find her.
Come on.
Hey, look at the size of it.
Living down here, the toxins of the river
must have driven him mad!
Get out of here now!
Alfred!
I'm, sorry!
- Alfred! Alfred! Stop!
- Stop!
Stop!
All right, everybody, listen up!
GCPD is now in lockdown.
Nobody goes in or out unless I say so.
She can look like anybody by now,
how are we supposed to find her?
Jim!
Barbara? What happened?
What do you mean what happened?
I've been attacked.
- Where did she go?
- Wait a minute.
How do we know it's really you?
Seriously?
This isn't proof enough?
- What the hell?
- That's her!
She's the impostor! Shoot her!
It's me, you idiot!
That sounds like Barbara.
Barbara...
tell me where we first met.
Don't shoot.
I'm leaving here.
Anyone tries to follow me, she dies.
- Shoot her!
- We can't risk it.
Stay back!
Bullock, wait!
I'm fine.
All right, take her to my office,
don't let her out of your sight.
Okay.
I cannot believe
that you told them about the sub
and that you're playing along
with this psychosis.
Obviously, he was gonna kill you.
I bought us time.
I have an idea.
If you can just keep him busy
and wait for the signal.
Wait, what's the signal?
Quit your jawing!
So Mr. Scarface and I
have discussed our options.
And the submarine sounds like a good plan.
And since we'll need the smart one
to build this hayburner,
he can keep sucking air.
But Penguin ain't so lucky.
Do it, Penn. Ventilate that mook.
I'm so sorry, Mr. Cobblepot.
I wish things would have
turned out differently.
Arthur, I want you to listen
to what I'm saying.
You accused me of manipulating you,
but what about him?
I never asked you to kill anybody.
- That is true.
- Hey.
And think of everything
that we went through together.
Sofia Falcone, getting cut off
from the mainland, starving.
You mean Penn was starving!
Fighting for scraps
while your dog ate steak!
I welcomed you into my home.
And, yes, I was not a good friend,
to you or to anyone.
It's why I'm alone.
But I saw you for what you are
and I value that.
That must be worth something.
Applesauce!
You're a liar and a thief.
All you do is take.
Take. Take.
And you never give anything.
You worked me to the bone.
Forced me to be your puppet.
Well, no more.
You hear me?
No more.
Take that! And that!
No.
Mr. Cobblepot.
You freed me.
How can I ever thank you?
Why did you do that?
He wasn't the threat.
- The dummy was the threat...
- Oswald.
I accept you for the person that you are.
Just as you accept me
for the cold logician that I am.
That's why this friendship is great.
And as friends,
I think we can both agree that
that lunatic had to be stopped.
Perhaps, Edward...
we really are meant for each other.
Jane!
I know you're up here!
Jane, I knew you'd be here.
I'm sorry.
It was my job to protect you
and I let you down.
You made Jane into a killer.
You and your friends,
there have to be consequences.
You killed three men already.
When is it enough?
When you're dead.
Put the gun down!
Shoot me.
You killed Jane years ago,
and you didn't even know how to shoot me?
Let me see your face.
Your real face.
Why? So you can see what a monster she is?
Hugo Strange only destroyed her face.
You destroyed her soul.
Let me see it.
Do you see?
Do you see what they did?
Jane...
we can work this out
just put the gun down.
The only way this ends
is with one of us dead.
Oh, hey, you're alive.
The nurse thinks the man that attacked us
will never recover.
The toxins in the river have done
irreparable damage to his brain.
Well, I just think it's a shame
we couldn't save
the rest of the people
who went missing, Master Bruce.
We should have went to Gordon
from the start.
- We were reckless.
- Ah, it's nonsense.
We took decisive action,
we saved a man's life.
The people in this city have suffered,
Master Bruce.
They need someone to protect them.
I agree.
But there are better ways
to find absolution.
I don't follow.
What happened to Wayne Manor
wasn't your fault.
I know you've been blaming yourself.
You didn't destroy our home, Alfred.
I feel like I did.
I feel like I wasn't strong enough
to fight Tetch
and that low life, Valeska.
I feel like because of my weakness,
you lost your last tie to the past.
You lost your home, Master Bruce.
I must never be that weak again.
Part of being a family
is that we can be strong for each other.
When did you get so smart?
I had a good teacher.
Victoria Cartwright killed her husband.
After we arrested her, she admitted it.
Later she recanted.
But the physical evidence wasn't there.
I was a new cop.
- I wanted to make detective...
- So you leaned on Jane?
Coerced a statement out of her
to put her mother away.
The woman was guilty.
Later I found out the husband...
beat the mother and Jane.
I didn't know until after.
The bartender overheard Jane
say something about,
"The kid's guilty too."
She meant the young cop.
She meant you.
I knew something was wrong.
I felt it.
I said something and they told me
to keep my trap shut,
just close the case, put a bow on it.
After a while I stopped feeling it.
And I went down that path for a long time.
Until I met you.
However much have changed...
I can't change the past.
I made that girl a killer.
What do you want from me, Harvey?
Forgiveness?
I can't give that to you.
I just needed you to know.